Preliminary Guide to the Duke University Museum of Art Records, 1962 - 2002 UA.07.10.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University Museum of Art records
1962 - 2002
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Museum of Art
UA.07.10.0001
17.5 Linear Feet
The Duke University Museum of Art opened to the public in 1969, in a renovated science building on the University's East Campus. In 1998, Duke alumnus Raymond D. Nasher donated funds to support construction of a new art museum at Duke University, the Nasher Museum of Art, set to open in 2005. Collection includes correspondence, administrative files, financial records, exhibit catalogs and publicity material, fund-raising files, clippings, photographs, and related records. Major subjects include the opening of the Museum of Art, the Brummer Collection of Medieval and Renaissance Art, and exhibits. Materials range in date from 1962 to 2002. English.
approx. 14,000 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Duke University Museum of Art Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer between 1970-2010.
Administrative History
The Duke University Museum of Art opened to the public in 1969, in a renovated science building on the University's East Campus. Planning for the Museum of Art began when the University acquired the Brummer Collection of Medieval and Renaissance Art in 1966. Other significant holdings included the George Harley Memorial Collection of African Art and a significant pre-Columbian collection, as well as Classical, American, and Russian art. As of 2004, the museum housed a collection of about 13,000 works ranging from ancient to contemporary art, and it regularly organized and featured a number of national traveling exhibitions.
The Museum's directors have been: Robert Moeller (1969-1970), William Heckscher (1970-1974), William Stars (1974-1982), John Spencer (1982-1986), Michael Mezzatesta (1987-2003), and Kimerly Rorschach (2004- ).
In 1998, Duke alumnus Raymond D. Nasher ('43) donated funds to support construction of a new art museum at Duke University. Construction began in 2000 on the Nasher Museum of Art, located between Duke's East and West campuses, and it was set to open in October 2005. Designed by Rafael Violy, the 65,000 square-foot facility was planned to become a cornerstone for cultural activities on campus, serving as a venue for performing arts events, lectures, film series and social gatherings.
Collection Overview
Collection includes correspondence, administrative files, financial records, exhibit catalogs and publicity material, fund-raising files, clippings, photographs, and related records. Major subjects include the opening of the Museum of Art, the Brummer Collection of Medieval and Renaissance Art, and exhibits. Materials range in date from 1962 to 2002.
Related Material
Museum of Art Reference Collection.
University Archives, Duke University.
Art Association Records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Clippings (information artifacts); Exhibition catalogs; Art -- North Carolina -- Durham -- Catalogs; Photographs; Art museums -- North Carolina -- Durham; Duke University. Museum of Art; Brummer, Ernest -- Art collections; Duke University. Museum of Art; Nasher Museum of Art at Duke University
- Container List [A81-98]
  - Exhibits, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - Exhibits and potential exhibits, 1967-1978 (Box 2)
  - Loan records, 1967-1974 (Box 2)
  - Financial records, budgets, insurance records, correspondence, circa 1964-1974 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, page proofs, layouts, and photos for exhibit catalogs, circa 1970-1972 (Box 3)
  - Administrative files, circa 1964-1978 (Box 4)
    - Outside services (Box 4)
    - Programs (Box 4)
    - Museum opening (Box 4)
    - Publicity (Box 4)
    - Publications (Box 4)
    - Donations (Box 4)
    - Photographs (Box 4)
    - Formation of graduate art program (Box 5)
    - Museum priorities (Box 5)
    - Correspondence (Box 5)
    - Planning and policy (Box 5)
    - Brummer materials (Box 5)
    - Photographs of exhibits, exhibit catalogs (Box 5)
    - Budgets and financial records (Box 6)
- Addition, 1986 [A86-12]
  - Development files, circa 1966-1982 (Box 7)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Development files are RESTRICTED for 25 years from the date of creation.
  - Development files, circa 1966-1982 (Box 8)
    All records in Box 8 (Development files, Benenson award files, and Financial records) are RESTRICTED for 25 years from the date of creation.
  - Benenson award files (Box 8)
  - Financial records, 1977-1979 (Box 8)
  - Exhibit catalogs, clippings, and other exhibit-related materials, circa 1963-1982 (Box 9)
    Scope and Contents note
    Exhibit catalogs include Ibram Lassaw, 1963; A Catalogue of Drawings and Prints by William Heckscher, 1967; Richard A. Miller, 1967; From Slave to Siren, 1971; DeGrazia of Arizona, 1972; The American Comic Strip, 1982; and others.
- Addition, 2004 [A2004-75]
  - Histories and general information, 1967-1984 and undated (Box 10)
  - Events and publicity, 1967-1992 (Box 10)
  - Building and maintenance, 1967-1969 (Box 10)
- Other Additions
  - Photographs, 1962-1965 and undated (Box 10)
  - Unprocessed clippings, exhibit catalogs, and publicity materials 1969-1970 (Box 10, Oversize-folder 11)
- UA2010-0022
  - General office files related to exhibitions, circa 1987-1994 (research materials, clippings, correspondence, purchase orders, publications and other) (20 folders) (Box 12)
  - R. Crumb exhibit general files, circa 1990-2002 (5 folders, 2 audiocassette tapes) (Box 12)
  - Interrogating Identity symposium and exhibition general files, circa 1992-1993 (3 folders) (Box 12)
  - Jackson Pollock exhibition general office files, circa 1992-1994 (10 folders) (Box 12)
  - General office files related to exhibitions, circa 1992-1994 (7 folders (Box 13)
  - Soho at Duke IV, In Search of Self, general files, circa 1993 (6 folders) (Box 13)
  - Homer exhibition, general files, circa 1993-1995 (9 folders) (Box 13)
  - Soho at Duke V, general files, circa 1993-1994 (2 folders) (Box 13)
  - Painting the Maya Universe: Royal Ceramics of the Classic Period, general files, circa 1993-1995 (12 folders) (Box 13)
  - Italian and Dutch paintings from the collection of Sarah Campbell Blaffer Foundation, general files and slides, circa 1994 (3 folders) (Box 14)
  - General files, including slides, related to exhibitions, circa 1993-1997 (13 folders) (Box 14)
  - A Generation of Antiquities: The Duke Classical Collection, 1964-1994, general files, circa 1994-1995 (2 folders) (Box 14)
  - Baltimore Portraits: Photography by Amos Badertscher, general files, including slides and photographs, circa 1995-1999 (5 folders) (Box 14)
  - House and Home: Spirits of the South, general files and slides, circa 1993-1995 (3 folders) (Box 14)
  - Jerusalem and the Holy Land Rediscovered, general files, circa 1994-1996 (5 folders) (Box 14)
  - General office files related to exhibitions, circa 1996-1998 (7 folders) (Box 15)
  - General files related to an exhibit on Venezuela, circa 1992-1997 (42 folders) (Box 15)
  - Duke University Museum of Art bound publications (Box 16)
- UA2013-0001
  - Information on exhibits proposed and presented and general information. Includes promotional as well as administrative materials. (Box 17)
  - Exhibition Schedule Folders, 1998-1999 (Box 17)
  - Chron - Jill Meredith, 1992-1993 (Box 17)
  - Jill Meredith, January-June, 1992 (Box 17)
  - July-December 1992 (Box 17)
  - Jill Meredith, January-June 1993 (Box 17)
  - Jill Meredith, July-December 1993 (Box 17)
  - Untitled, flyers for The Art Museums of Louis I. Kahn (Box 17)
  - Kahn Photos (Box 17)
  - Kahn Photos (Box 17)
  - Kahn (Box 17)
  - 3rd Annual Brummer Society Dinner (Box 17)
  - Painting the Maya Universe: Royal Ceramics of the Classic Period (Box 17)
  - Religion & Art pamphlet by Richard Bernheimer (Box 17)
  - Beyond Mere Likeness: Portraits from Africa and the African Diaspora (Box 17)
  - Arthur B. Davies (Box 17)
  - Contemporary Latin American Art (Box 17)
  - Weavers of the Andes, Keeper of Tradition (Box 17)
  - Reflections of Medicine, The Graphic Art (Box 17)
  - Russian Conceptual Art, newspaper clippings and press releases (Box 17)
  - General Newspaper Clippings (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous Invitations and Brochures (Box 17)
  - Information on exhibits proposed and presented and general information. Includes promotional as well as administrative materials. (Box 18)
  - R.B. Kitaj September-December, 2001 (Box 18)
  - Exhibition Planning (Kitaj) (Box 18)
  - Academic Eye: Price (Box 18)
  - March 29, 2001-May 27, 2001, Academic Eye Reynolds Price Collection (Box 18)
  - Correspondnce, Reynolds Price Collection Academic Eye, 2001 (Box 18)
  - Background/Research (Reynolds Price Collection Academic Eye) (Box 18)
  - Catalogue (Reynolds Price Collection Academic Eye) (Box 18)
  - Publications (Reynolds Price Collection Academic Eye) (Box 18)
  - Publications (Reynolds Price Collection Academic Eye) (Box 18)
  - Budget (Reynolds Price Collection Academic Eye) (Box 18)
  - January 26, 2001-March 18, 2001, Mary Lou Williams: In Her Own Right (Box 18)
  - Mary Lou Williams: In Her Own Right, Correspondence (Box 18)
  - Exhibit File: Mary Lou Williams, Research/Background (Box 18)
  - Mary Lou Williams, Budgeting (Box 18)
  - Publications, Mary Lou Williams: In Her Own Right (Box 18)
  - Checklist, Mary Lou Williams: In Her Own Right (Box 18)
  - Mary Lou Williams: In Her Own Right January-March 2001 (Box 18)
  - Exhibition Planning (with photos), Mary Lou Williams exhibit (Box 18)
  - Correspondence, Mary Lou Williams exhibit (Box 18)
  - Checklist, Mary Lou Williams exhibit (Box 18)
  - Installations, Mary Lou Williams exhibit (Box 18)
  - Publicity and Opening, Mary Lou Williams exhibit (Box 18)
  - To Conserve a Legacy, October 15-December 1, 2000 (Box 18)
  - Exhibition Planning, Legacy exhibit (Box 18)
  - Budget and Expenses, Legacy exhibit (Box 18)
  - Checklist, Legacy exhibit (Box 18)
  - Installations, Legacy exhibit (Box 18)
  - SAVy Selects: Rep./Other, April 6-May 14, 2000 (Box 18)
  - Checklists, SAVy Selects (Box 18)
  - Installations, SAVy Selects (Box 18)
  - Christian Haye Curates: Harlem Project, February 20-April 2, 2000 (Box 18)
  - Research/Background Information, Christian Haye Curates (Box 18)
  - Planning, Christian Haye Curates (Box 18)
  - Correspondence, Christian Haye Curates (Box 18)
  - Pietrasanta/New York: Caio Fonseca, October 6-December 5, 2000 (Box 18)
  - Research/Background Information, Pietrasanta (includes a booklet of color photographs) (Box 18)
  - Ilya Kabakov: The Boat of My Life, June 26-October 17, 1999 (Box 18)
  - Research/Background Information, Kabakov (Box 18)
  - Planning, Kabakov (Box 18)
  - Beyond Brancusi: John Safer, September 29-November 7, 1999 (Box 18)
  - Checklist, Beyond Brancusi (Box 18)
  - Research/Background Information, Beyond Brancusi (Box 18)
  - About Face: Works on Paper (Box 18)
  - Installation, About Face (Box 18)
  - Labels, About Face (Box 18)
  - Research/Background Information, About Face (Box 18)
  - Planning, About Face (Box 18)
  - Checklist, About Face (Box 18)
  - Critic's Choice: Julia Morton, April 13-May 28, 2000 (Box 18)
  - Checklist, Julia Morton (Box 18)
  - Correspondence, Julia Morton (Box 18)
  - Student Curated Exhibit XII, April-June 2001 (Box 18)
  - List of Student Exhibits (Box 18)
  - Budget and Expenses, Student Curated Exhibit XII (Box 18)
  - Exhibition Planning, Student Curated Exhibit XII (Box 18)
  - Publicity and Opening, Student Curated Exhibit XII (Box 18)
  - Installations, Student Curated Exhibit XII (Box 18)
  - Correspondence, Student Curated Exhibit XII (Box 18)
  - October-December 2001, Academic Eye II: Ariel Dorfman (Box 18)
  - Correspondences, Ariel Dorfman (Box 18)
  - Publications, Ariel Dorfman (Box 18)
  - Catalogue, Ariel Dorfman (Box 18)
  - Budget, Ariel Dorfman (Box 18)
  - April 16-June 10, 2001, Student Curators XII: Contemporary Issues in Asian Art (Box 18)
  - Correspondences, Contemporary Issues in Asian Art (Box 18)
  - Exhibit File Student-Curated Show Background/Research, Contemporary Issues in Asian Art (Box 18)
  - Budget [2], Contemporary Issues in Asian Art (Box 18)
  - Publications, Contemporary Issues in Asian Art (Box 18)
  - DUMA SAVY PROGRAM SAVY SHOW - 2001 Publications (Box 18)
  - Exhibit File Student-Curated Show Checklist, Contemporary Issues in Asian Art (Box 18)
  - Checklist, Contemporary Issues in Asian Art (Box 18)
  - Research, Contemporary Issues in Asian Art (Box 18)
  - August 16-October 28, 2001, Rodolfo Abularach: Apocalyptic Landscapes (Box 18)
  - Budget/Expenses, Apocalyptic Landscapes (Box 18)
  - Presentation/Catalogue, Apocalyptic Landscapes (Box 18)
  - Correspondences, Apocalyptic Landscapes (Box 18)
  - Publications, Apocalyptic Landscapes (Box 18)
  - Registrar Information, Apocalyptic Landscapes (Box 18)
  - Research/Background, Apocalyptic Landscapes (Box 18)
  - Photographs/Slides, Apocalyptic Landscapes (Box 18)
  - November 8-December 21, 2001, Giorgio de Chirico: Legacy and Connoisseurship--A Student Curated Exhibit (Box 18)
  - Exhibition File: "de Chirico--Tempest" (Box 18)
  - January 24-March 24, 2002, Dancing Ink: Calligraphy of Wang Fangyu (Box 18)
  - Exhibition File: Dancing Ink: Calligraphy of Wang Fangyu (Box 18)
  - August 23-October 27, 2002, Missing: Documenting the Spontaneous Memorials of 9/11 (Box 18)
  - September 11 Municipal Arts Society (Box 18)
  - November 14, 2002-February 2, 2003, Pedro Figari (1861-1938): Lines of Uruguayan Life, A Student Curated Exhibit (Box 18)
  - Correspondences, Pedro Figari exhibit (Box 18)
  - Checklist, Pedro Figari exhibit (Box 18)
  - Research/Background, Pedro Figari exhibit (Box 18)
  - Figari's Catalogue (Box 18)
  - Figari's Translations (Box 18)
  - Information on exhibits proposed and presented and general information. Includes promotional as well as administrative materials. (Box 19)
  - Acquitions (Box 19)
  - Hugo Robus (Box 19)
  - Medieval Manuscript (Box 19)
  - Louis K. Meisel (Box 19)
  - Tulie Speight (Box 19)
  - Goncharov (Box 19)
  - Robert Capen (Box 19)
  - Brummer Exhibition Loan Objects (Box 19)
  - Exhibitions 1996-1997 (Box 19)
  - Correspondence 1993-1994, Director's Office (Box 19)
  - Woman Artists MNWA Show, Exhibition Labels (Box 19)
  - NMWA Photographs (Box 19)
  - Exhibit: Royal Palace (Box 19)
  - Ellen Biddle Shipman Exhibition (Box 19)
  - Andrei Erofeer (Tsaritsino Museum Show) (Box 19)
  - Saffer (Box 19)
  - Monumental Propaganda Exhibition, 94/95 (Box 19)
  - Romare Bearden (Box 19)
  - DUMA Student Curators, 1988-1999 (Box 19)
  - Gospel Concert Fall 1989, Future Exhibits (Box 19)
  - Artificial Reality (Box 19)
  - Exhibit File: Amazon Show (Box 19)
  - Exhibition File: Socialist Realism (Box 19)
  - 1994 Frederick II exhibition/WAG (Box 19)
  - Exhibitions 97-98 (Box 19)
  - Nabatoff (Box 19)
  - VRA Bulletin, Winter 2005, volume 31, number 2 (Box 19)
  - DUMA Magazine [7] (Box 19)
  - William S. Heckschaw, and Director of the DUMA (Box 19)
  - Research Opportunities in Renaissance Drama: XIII-XIV (Box 19)
  - Guests (Box 19)